School of the Museum of Fine Arts Records UA133
Tufts Archival Research Center
School of the Museum of Fine Arts Records
1875 -- 2022
1960 -- 2010
Tufts Archival Research Center
Department of Art and Art History
Department of Art and the History of Art and Architecture
UA133
681.4 Linear Feet 542 record cartons; 54 bound items; 6 card catalog boxes/12 drawers; 8 document boxes; 1 half document box; 6 oversize boxes; 5 card boxes; 1 oversize flat file; 1 artifact box; 1 index-card box; and 47 scrapbooks.
1 Web sites
The School of the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston became affiliated with Tufts College in 1945, and in July 2016 officially became part of Tufts University's School of Arts and Sciences. This collection contains records of the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, including administrative files, exhibition files, course descriptions, and student records, from 1875 to 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are noted in the Detailed Contents List in each series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Department of Art and History, 2011 -- 2013, the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, 2016 -- 2021, and the Museum of Fine Arts, 2019. The 2019 accession was previously transferred from the SMFA to the MFA archives. Student work in the 2021 accessions was donated by students in 2021.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into fifteen series: Administrative records; Admissions records; Communications Office records; Course descriptions and requirements; Student Affairs records; Dean's Office records; Development records; Exhibitions and public programs records; Master of Fine Arts program records; Office of the Provost records; Audiovisual materials; Photographs; Publications; 2019 accessions; and Web crawls.
Biographical / Historical
The School of the Museum of Fine Arts (SMFA) was established in 1876 when the Trustees of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts (MFA) set aside rooms for an art school in the newly opened Copley Square building. Originally called the School of Painting and Drawing, in 1901 it was fully incorporated into the museum and renamed the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, sometimes called the Boston Museum School or simply the Museum School. In 1945, the SMFA and Tufts College began their partnership with a teacher training program. Additional programs and partnerships soon followed and in July 2016, the SMFA officially became part of Tufts University's School of Arts and Sciences.
In 1876 the School of Painting and Drawing was established at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts in the new Copley Square building. Eight students were enrolled in 1877 and by 1879 the school had a total of 160 students, the majority of them women. Also in 1879, the Art Student Association was founded by students from the school; the Association later changed its name to The Copley Society which still operates today as the oldest non-profit art association in the nation. The Museum of Fine Arts moved in 1909 to a new location on Huntington Avenue and the school moved with it. In 1927, the school moved out of its buildings on the Museum of Fine Arts lot into the building designed by Guy Lowell at 230 The Fenway.
The School of the Museum of Fine Arts offered courses in drawing, graphic arts, painting, sculpture, ceramics, jewelry, silversmithing, and commercial art. The curriculum was traditional, with foundation courses required in the first two years of the program. In 1968, however, faculty hierarchies were eliminated, all students had access to all courses, and the review board system (student artwork is judged at the end of the term by a board of staff and students, in place of grades) was put in place. More recently, the curriculum has expanded to include photography, video arts, and performance art. The school trained many well-known artists, including Cy Twombley (1928-2011), Jim Dine (1935-), and Ellsworth Kelly (1923-2015).
The relationship between Tufts College and the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, or the "Museum School," began in the 1943-1944 academic year when School of the Museum of Fine Arts Professor Russell T. Smith began to teach part-time at Tufts. In 1945, Tufts College of Special Studies and the School of the Museum of Fine Arts began a partnership which allowed students at Tufts to take electives in creative arts at the Museum School, and Museum School students to take education courses to be certified to teach art. The partnership was part of a larger effort to provide opportunities to students outside of the Tufts College campuses. The School of the Museum of Fine Arts was not accredited to give out degrees and instead granted diplomas and certificates while the Bachelor of Science in Education was conferred by Tufts College. The partnership expanded over the years and students from the Museum School were granted master's as well as bachelor's degrees from Tufts University.
In July 2016, the SMFA officially became part of Tufts University's School of Arts and Sciences. The SMFA now offers both undergraduate and graduate programs, as well as a 5-year dual-degree program (BA/BS and BFA).
Custodial History
Tufts University acquired the School of the Museum of Fine Arts on July 1, 2016, after a 70-year partnership with the School on a joint dual-degree program. DCA staff were not able to survey records or discuss records with SMFA staff while negotiations for this aquisition were underway. When DCA staff arrived at the SMFA the week before the acquisition, most SMFA staff had already left the School, leaving behind a subset of records in boxes and filing cabinets. That summer DCA staff selected and packed additional records in consultation with the remaining (or new) staff from Academic Affairs, Communication and Marketing, Development, Exhibitions and Public Programs, and the Library. These records were received at DCA in September, 2016, and a second transfer from the Library was received in November, 2016. Records in Series 5 were maintained in SMFA's Student Services file room in the Mission Hill building until a July 2017 digitization project. Digiscribe New England scanned all transcripts and Review Board comments at their Norwood, MA facility, July-November 2017. On February 13, 2018 the records were transferred from the Digiscribe facility to DCA's off-site storage at Iron Mountain, under the supervision of Liz Francis, University Records Manager. Custody of the records was transferred to DCA by JoAnn Jack, Registrar, ASE later that week. Records in Series 14 were previously transferred from the SMFA to the Museum of Fine Arts Archives and were then transferred to DCA in August 2019.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records of the School of the Museum of Fine Arts (SMFA), including administrative records, office records, exhibition files, course descriptions, and student records, from 1875 to 2018. Student records form the bulk of the collection, with the majority dating from 1945-2015. The Exhibition and public programing materials also make up a large part of the collection and consist of slides of artwork and exhibitions as well as event calendars, art loan documentation, exhibition catalogs, and exhibition planning documents. The collection also includes audiovisual materials, clippings, photographs, publications, and scrapbooks. In addition to documenting the administration of the SMFA, topics covered by material in this collection include annual exhibitions such as the Traveling Scholars and 5th Year Exhibition, student life, and alumni activities.
Department and offices represented in the collection include Admissions; Communications; Student Affairs; the Dean's Office; Development; Exhibitions and Public Programs; the Master of Fine Arts program; the Office of the Provost; the Board of Governors; and the SMFA School Council. Admissions materials mainly consist of records created by the office such as booklets and pamphlets about admissions. Communications Office records comprise office files as well as publications produced for other departments. The Dean's Office records consist of correspondence, materials relating to the Board of Governors, meeting materials, proposals, reports, school budgets, and self-study materials for the SMFA. The Development records include Alumni Relations materials such as slides of artwork, as well as correspondence, reports, publicity material, meeting minutes, and donor information. The Master of Fine Arts program records contain admissions material, student records, and records documenting student life. The Office of the Provost records contain syllabi, faculty curricula vitae, and reports. Audiovisual materials consist of VHS, U-matic, and U-maticS tapes of lectures and exhibition pieces. Scrapbooks contain clippings, invitations, itineraries, pamphlets, photographs, postcards, tickets, and narrative descriptions of artwork, museums, and travel across Europe.
Art--Study and teaching; Teaching and learning; Curriculum and Instruction; Greater Boston arts; Curriculum and Instruction -- Student Work; Advancement; Admissions and Recruitment; Museum of Fine Arts, Boston. School
- Administrative records, circa 1900 -- 2012; UA133.001; 10.08 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains administrative files from the SMFA dating from circa 1940 to 2012. These files include annual reports; board and committee meeting minutes; long range and strategic planning materials; correspondence; clippings; and related material from the executive committee and administrative offices. This series also contains materials relating to the Museum School contract with Tufts University including correspondence dating from 1945 to 1977.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically by accession date.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This series may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
  - Museum School contract and correspondence, 1945 -- 1977; UA133.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Open for research.
    Bulk of materials is from the 1970s.
  - Degree granting authority, 1954; UA133.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1970 -- 1979; UA133.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    Date range is approximate.
  - Counseling Center pamphlet, 1970 -- 2000; UA133.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - September 2016 acessions, circa 1900 -- 2012; UA133.001.001; 4.82 Linear Feet
    This sub-series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This sub-series may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
    This sub-series is arranged chronologically.
    Scope and content note: This sub-series contains administration records, annual reports, board and committee meeting minutes, committee reports, correspondence, and planning documents.
    - Annual reports 1900-1939; Board and committee meeting minutes 1996-1999, 1900 -- 1939, 1996 -- 1999; UA133.001.001.025 (Box 25)
      20 years from date of creation.
    - Annual reports; Long range and strategic planning materials, circa 1940 -- 2008; UA133.001.001.009 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, circa 1944 -- 1946; UA133.001.001.010 (Box 10)
    - Administration records, circa 1989 -- 2012; UA133.001.001.011 (Box 11)
    - Committee reports, 2002 -- 2003; UA133.001.001.060 (Box 60)
  - January 2017 accession, 1877 -- 2010; UA133.001.002; 3.42 Linear Feet 2 record cartons, 1 card catalog box/2 drawers
    This sub-series is open for research.
    This sub-series contains annual reports, and card indices documenting committee work, correspondence, public programs, and administration and committee meetings.
    - Annual Reports, 1877 -- 1957; UA133.001.002.034 (Box 34)
      - First Annual Report, 1876 -- 1877; UA133.001855; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 4.63 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Second Annual Report, 1877 -- 1878; UA133.001856; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.78 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Third Annual Report, 1878 -- 1879; UA133.001857; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 5.6 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Fourth Annual Report, 1880 -- 1881; UA133.001858; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.87 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Fifth Annual Report, 1881 -- 1882; UA133.001859; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.47 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Seventh Annual Report, 1882 -- 1883; UA133.001860; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.4 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Eighth Annual Report, 1883 -- 1884; UA133.001861; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 4.46 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Ninth Annual Report, 1884 -- 1885; UA133.001862; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 4.31 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Tenth Annual Report, 1885 -- 1886; UA133.001863; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 8.51 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Thirty-sixth Annual Report for the Year Ending June 1, 1912, 1911 -- 1912; UA133.001864; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.5 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Thirty-seventh Annual Report for the Year Ending May 1, 1913, 1912 -- 1913; UA133.001865; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.82 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1914 -- 1915; UA133.001866; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.89 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1916 -- 1917; UA133.001867; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.08 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1917 -- 1918; UA133.001868; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.86 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1918 -- 1919; UA133.001869; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 2.95 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1919 -- 1920; UA133.001870; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.07 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1920 -- 1921; UA133.001871; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 3.58 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1921 -- 1922; UA133.001872; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 4.35 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1922 -- 1923; UA133.001873; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 10.8 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1923 -- 1924; UA133.001874; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 17.2 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1924 -- 1925; UA133.001875; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 13.5 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1925 -- 1926; UA133.001876; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 16.2 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1926 -- 1927; UA133.001877; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 14.2 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1927 -- 1928; UA133.001878; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 15.3 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1928 -- 1929; UA133.001879; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 16.6 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1929 -- 1930; UA133.001880; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 19.1 Megabytes (Box 34)
      - Annual Circular, 1930 -- 1931; UA133.001881; 1 Volumes; 1 Digital Object(s); 20.6 Megabytes (Box 34)
    - Card index of committee work, circa 1879 -- 1930; UA133.001.002.005 (Box 5)
    - Index of Administration and Committee Meetings, 1879 -- 1930; UA133.001.002.018 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence and public programs, circa 2000 -- 2010; UA133.001.002.063 (Box 63)
  - November 2017 accession, circa 2009 -- 2011; UA133.001.003; 0.2 Linear Feet
    This sub-series is arranged in received order.
    This sub-series contains program information and itineraries on SMFA's alternative spring break in New Orleans, LA, as well as information on SMFA's internship and exchange program with Xavier University and the New Orleans Women Artists Collective.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Transferred by Liz Francis, 2017, accession UA-2018-019.
    - SMFA in NOLA (Alternative Spring Break), 2009; UA133.001.003.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
    - SMFA in NOLA (Alternative Spring Break), 2010; UA133.001.003.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
    - SMFA in NOLA (Alternative Spring Break), 2011; UA133.001.003.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
    - SMFA, New Orleans Women Artists Collective, Xavier University, circa 2011; UA133.001.003.002.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
    - SMFA in NOLA, 2010 -- 2011; UA133.001.003.002.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - December 2017 accession, circa 1940 -- 1969; UA133.001.004; 0.6 Linear Feet 1 archival box
    Transferred by Darin Murphy, 2017, accession UA-2018-026.
    This sub-series contains card catalog records including student course records; former student and instructor contact information; non-SMFA art organization contact information; and other miscellaneous records.
    Student records and development records are closed 75 years from the date of creation. Administrative records are closed 20 years from the date of creation. This sub-series may require review before it is available for use; please contact DCA for further details.
    - Student and instructor records, art organizations, misc. card catalog records, circa 1940 -- 1969; UA133.001.004.088; 0.6 Linear Feet 1 archival box (Box 88)
      Student records and development records are closed 75 years from the date of creation. Administrative records are closed 20 years from the date of creation.
  - September 2021 accessions, circa 1968 -- 2010; UA133.001848; 1 Linear Feet
    Transferred by Darin Murphy, Assistant Director, W. Van Alan Clark, Jr. Library, 2021, accession UA-2022-020.
    This sub-series contains faculty directories, faculty handbooks, New England Association of Schools and Colleges self-study records, strategic plans, Art Safety and Hazardous Materials Plan, and SMFA history material.
    - Faculty directories, New England Association of Schools and Colleges self-study, and planning and history records, circa 1968 -- 2010; UA133.001849 (Box 636)
      Faculty directories, faculty handbooks, New England Association of Schools and Colleges self-study records, strategic plans, Art Safety and Hazardous Materials Plan, and SMFA history material.
- Admissions records, circa 1988 -- 2015; UA133.002; 0.8 Linear Feet
  This series is open for research.
  This series contains admissions records from the SMFA dating from circa 1988 to 2015. These records include admissions catalogs, information booklets, and other admissions advertising materials. Many of the admissions catalogs contain course descriptions, financial aid information, and academic calendars. This series contains no undergraduate student applications. Applications to the Master of Fine Arts program are in series 9: Master of Fine Arts program records.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Catalogs and booklets, circa 1988 -- 2015; UA133.002.011 (Box 11)
    Series 2: Admissions records are open for research. The other series in this box is closed for 20 years from date of creation.
  - Admissions catalogs, 2002 -- 2009; UA133.002.060 (Box 60)
- Communications Office records, circa 1970 -- 2016; UA133.003; 15.84 Linear Feet
  This series contains records from the Marketing and Communications office dating from circa 1969 to 2016. These records include annual art sale records, course catalogs, marketing materials, publications, and exhibit photographs and slides.
  Course catalogs include those of the Continuing Education and Summer programs. Marketing materials include studies, press kits, clippings, and media coverage reports. Printed materials and publications comprise booklets, fliers, pamphlets, and viewbooks created by the Communications office for the Admissions, Development, Exhibitions, and Student Affairs departments. This series also contains CDs and DVDs of artists' work and records for the Medal Award, an annual award presented to an individual whose work furthers the development and understanding of contemporary art.
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Aprons, t-shirt, and bandana, circa 2011; UA133.003.043 (Box 43)
  - Clippings, circa 1970 -- 2011; UA133.003.010 (Box 10)
  - Clippings, circa 1990 -- 2001; UA133.003.050 (Box 50)
  - Clippings and media coverage reports, circa 1983 -- 2012; UA133.003.060 (Box 60)
  - Clippings, media coverage reports, press releases, and publications, circa 1997 -- 2014; UA133.003.054 (Box 54)
  - Communications CDs and DVDs, circa 1990 -- 2016; UA133.003.071 (Box 71)
  - Communications CDs and DVDs, circa 1990 -- 2016; UA133.003.070 (Box 70)
  - Marketing study, media coverage reports, negatives, photographs, and slides, circa 1998 -- 2003; UA133.003.051 (Box 51)
  - Media coverage reports, circa 1990 -- 2016; UA133.003.048 (Box 48)
  - Photographs, printed material, publications, and slides, circa 1990 -- 2016; UA133.003.049 (Box 49)
  - Press kits, clippings, media coverage reports, publications, and slides, circa 1995 -- 2007; UA133.003.047 (Box 47)
  - Publications, 2012 -- 2016; UA133.003.046 (Box 46)
  - Publications, 2007 -- 2011; UA133.003.053 (Box 53)
  - Publications and art sale records, circa 2004 -- 2006; UA133.003.056 (Box 56)
  - Slides, photographs, clippings, media coverage reports, press kits and releases, publications, circa 1988 -- 2004; UA133.003.052 (Box 52)
- Course descriptions and requirements, circa 1969 -- 2016; UA133.004; 1.27 Linear Feet
  This series contains SMFA course catalogs and course descriptions dating from 1969 to 2016. Evening course, Summer School, and Continuing Education program catalogs are included in this series. The course catalogs often contain information about the academic calendar and sometimes contain admissions information. This set of course catalogs is incomplete, and there are gaps in some years.
  - Course descriptions, 1969 -- 1975; UA133.004.001.00011 (Box 1)
    Materials were found in the Vault of Ballou Hall.
  - Course descriptions and catalogs, circa 1971 -- 2016; UA133.004.004 (Box 4)
  - Courses and catalog, 1979; UA133.004.001.00012 (Box 1)
- Student Affairs records, circa 1876 -- 2016; UA133.005; 469.19 Linear Feet 388 record cartons; 5 card catalog boxes/10 drawers; 5 card boxes
  This series contains records from the Student Affairs office. These records consist mainly of student records dating from 1876 to 2016, which may include information about years of attendance, classes, grades, scholarships, and awards, as well as remarks and notes from faculty members about students. This series also contains admissions, enrollment, and financial aid booklets; advertising material such as brochures, postcards, and posters; clippings; housing and building reports; photographic negatives; scrapbooks; and artifacts. Artifacts consist of uniforms for the Arts Cheerleaders, a performance organization founded by SMFA alumni in 2007 which raised awareness for arts education. More material related to the Arts Cheerleaders can be found in Series 7: Development records.
  - September 2016 accessions, circa 1990 -- 2015; UA133.005.001; 2.02 Linear Feet
    This sub-series contains booklets, advertising materials, clippings, reports, and negatives from the Student Affairs department, as well as an Arts Cheerleader uniform found in the Student Affairs office and an SMFA banner.
    This sub-series is arranged alphabetically.
    - Booklets, advertising materials, clippings, reports, and negatives, circa 1996 -- 2015; UA133.005.001.063 (Box 63)
    - Cheerleader uniforms, 1995; UA133.005.001.061 (Box 61)
    - SMFA banner, circa 1990 -- 2000; UA133.005.001.026 (Box 26)
  - January 2017 accession, circa 1876 -- 2010; UA133.005.002; 12.17 Linear Feet
    Transferred by the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, 2017, accession UA-2017-051.
    This sub-series is arranged in rough chronological order.
    Custodial History
    Material originally housed in the School of Museum of Fine Arts W. Van Alan Clark, Jr. Library.
    Existence and Location of Originals